Finding Aid for the Robert A. McGaw Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Robert A. McGaw Papers
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0275
9.17 linear_feet
Biography
Robert Armistead McGaw served on the Vanderbilt University administration staff for 31 years from 1948 to 1979. He started his career at Vanderbilt as assistant to Chancellor Harvie Branscomb in charge of publications, the first person to fill such a role at the University. In 1964 he was appointed Secretary of the University by Alexander Heard, and held that position until his retirement in 1979.
McGaw was born in Nashville, TN March 25, 1914 to Samuel M. and Bonnie Howard McGaw. A product of Nashville public schools, he graduated from Hume Fogg High School in 1931. Accepted into Vanderbilt University, he only attended for 1 year before he went to work at the Nashville Banner in the sport department under Vanderbilt Alumnus Fred Russell. In 1936 he went work at Methodist Publishing House where he served as magazine editor, advertising manager, and director of personnel and public relations. He stayed at Methodist Publishing House till his move Vanderbilt, with the exception of the leave of absence he took to serve in the United States Marine Corps as a celestial navigator in the Pacific Arena of WWII.
In addition to his job as Secretary of the University, McGaw was also the executive secretary of Alumni relations, director of information and publications, and chief editor and designer of Vanderbilt publications. As a designer McGaw was responsible for creating the Vanderbilt shield, stationary, and diploma. Two significant works he wrote and published for Vanderbilt were Vanderbilt: A Brief History (1973) and The Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History (1978).
Outside of Vanderbilt, McGaw was an active member in Nashville society. He was a charter member of the Metro Historical Commission, a member of the Tennessee Historical Society and the Old Oak Literary Club, for which he wrote many essays and served as secretary for 40 years. He was also a lifelong member of West End Methodist Church. McGaw had one son, John Early McGaw, with his wife Elizabeth Early McGaw. He died of cancer on June 30, 2003 at the age of 89.
Scope and Content Note
The Robert A. McGaw Papers are comprised of four series; Vanderbilt University, Designs, Writings and WWII. The papers follow closely McGaw’s career and are important to anyone interested in the history of the university. Of special note is the Design Series where McGaw assisted in re-designing the symbols of the university in the 1970s.
- Vanderbilt Papers, A-H
  - Allard, David Preston, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Announcement, Vanderbilt 1876-83 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art, examples of Vanderbilt, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Athletics 1992-93 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Harvie Branscomb 1970-98 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt”, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Centennial, Vanderbilt 1973-75 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Code of By-Laws, Vanderbilt, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Colors, Vanderbilt 1949-97 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Friends of the Library, Constitution & Members 1978-85 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Friends of the Library 1979-97 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Football History, Vanderbilt 1954-55 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fugitives & Agrarians Plaques, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Garland, Landon & Lagemann, Robert, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gary Gore Retirement, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - “Hands Across the Sea” Schools of Nashville, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Heard, Alexander, 1952-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Vanderbilt Papers, I-M
  - Inauguration, Vanderbilt, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rudolph Kampmeier Department of Medicine 1979-80 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - John F. Kennedy Visit 30 th Anniversary, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - James Lawson 1960-98 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letterhead, Vanderbilt, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Library Celebration 1991-98 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Living Endowment 1938-53 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Map Collection, Catalog & Contributions 1988-98 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Map Collection, Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Map Collection, Newspaper, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Map Collection, Correspondence & misc., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Robert A. McGaw at Vanderbilt to, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Robert A. McGaw at Vanderbilt 1950-59 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Robert A. McGaw at Vanderbilt 1960-62 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Vanderbilt Papers, M-S
  - Robert A. McGaw at Vanderbilt 1962-79 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Methodist Publishing House, 1897-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mims, Puryear 1954-98 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Nashville Historic Markers, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Oak Leaves & Acorns, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Office of Information & Publications 1950-63 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Old Gym becomes Art Gallery, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographic Archive, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pictures at Vanderbilt, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Publication Corrections letters 1994-97 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sarratt Commons Art – Alphabets, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Madison Sarratt letter to R. Forrestor, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Seal, Vanderbilt, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Secretary of the University 1963-79 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Semi-Centennial of Vanderbilt, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Vanderbilt Papers, S-T
  - Shield Origins 1954-95 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Shield, Vanderbilt University, requests for adoption, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Songs of Vanderbilt, 1897-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Special Collections Correspondence 1967-91 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Symbols of Vanderbilt, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Television News Archive, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Gates P. Thruston Collection – Trust Agreement, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gates P. Thruston Collection Photos 1964-73 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Trees at Vanderbilt 1967-94 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Vanderbilt Papers, U-Z
  - “Uncommon Men” Vanderbilt Magazine, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - United Nations Visits Vanderbilt, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - University Press, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - University Charter, Vanderbilt 1872-73 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Vanderbilt, Cornelius “In Memoriam”, 1877 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Vanderbilt History & Purpose 1908-79 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Vanderbilt Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Vanderbilt Misc. Printed Pieces, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Vanderbilt Oral History Project 1996-99 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Vanderbilt University Sports “Top 20 Moments”, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Vanderbilt Stadium, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Vanderbilt Television News Archive, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - “Vanderbilt Trees” Daily American Article, 1878 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - West End Amoco 1996-98 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Witham, C. letters to Vanderbilt President & Robert A. McGaw, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Wyatt, Joe B. 1983-95 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Designs, A-E
  - Chronological list of Designs by Robert McGaw, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Association 1948-58 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Apartments for Married Students, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Art Drama Music, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Art Gallery, Vanderbilt, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 6. Astronomy at Vanderbilt, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Ballet Festival, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Belle Meade Mansion, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Benedict, A.B. Stained Glass, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Benton Chapel Organ, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The Black Student at Vanderbilt, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Book Jackets 1954-55 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Brazil President Dutra, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Calendar, Vanderbilt, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Capitol Dots & Lines 1956-57 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Campus Maps 1952, 58, 65 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Carmichael Portrait, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Centennial 1973-75 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Chancellor’s Collar, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Chancellor’s Cup, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Christianity & Democracy, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Christmas Cards 1947-76 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Code of By-Laws, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Commencement Program, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Dedication of Science Center, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Diploma, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Divinity School Dedication, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - 28. Dyer Observatory, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Emeritus Faculty Tray, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - 30. Engineering School Information, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Designs, F-P
  - Faculty Assembly 1962-82 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Friends of the Library, 1974-75, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Fugitives 1956 & 69 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Fulfilling the Conception of a Grand University, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General Information, Vanderbilt, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Goodpasture & Morgan, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Graduate School Almanac, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Avery Handly Catalogue, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Alexander Heard Installation, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Alexander Heard Speeches 1963-70 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Historic American Buildings Survey Exhibit, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - History Department News Letters 1963 & 76 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Horn, Stanley F. Tennessee’s War, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Law School Dedication, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Major Benefactors of Vanderbilt, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Medicine, School of Rules & Procedures, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Memorial Gymnasium 1st Sale of Tickets, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Methodist Publishing House 1941, 48 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Monday Evening Lectures, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Nashville Community Playhouse “Eve of St. Mark”, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Nursing, School of, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - “Occasion Honoring Faculty for Books Published”, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Phi Beta Kappa certificate, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Pilcher, Cobb in Memoriam, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Plaque Underwood, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - “Please Let It Be”, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - President of the United States, JF Kennedy, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Proceedings Harold Vanderbilt Statue, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Psychotherapy & Ministry Spring Convocation Religion, School of, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Designs, R-Z
  - Rand, Frank C. In Memoriam, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Resolutions by Vanderbilt Board of Trust 1970-76 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Seventy-Fifth Anniversary, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Shield Vanderbilt, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Stadium Expansion, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - State of the University, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Stationary, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Stevenson Center, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Sutherland Prize, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Television News Index & Abstracts, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Tennessee Scenic Rivers Association, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - “These Hundred Acres”, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - “Ties Which Should Exist”, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - United Nations of Vanderbilt, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - “Vanderbilt Divinity School: a history”, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - “Vanderbilt in France”, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Vanderbilt Gazette, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Vanderbilt Miscellany 1950-76 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - “Viewpoint”, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - “Wages, Prices, Profits and Productivity”, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - “Conversation Piece & Other Poems” 1965-66 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Wills, Jesse “A Diversity of Interests”, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Wills, Jesse “Early & Late: Fugitive Poems & Others“, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Wills, Jesse “Meditations On the American Indian”, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Wills, Jesse “Nashville & Other Poems”, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Writings, A-F
  - Alumni Association (about) 1952-55 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - “An Arrowhead Speaker” short story, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Branscomb: “Purely Academic”, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt” 2nd edition 1982-84 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt” 1st edition, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt” Manuscript Development 1964-71 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt” comments 1964-77 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt” Documentation, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - “A Brief History of Vanderbilt” McGaw Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - “The Catholic Church in Tennessee” by Thomas Stritch, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - “City of Cedars”, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - “Duty” the United Daughters of the Confederacy, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - “CRS Profile: Sam M. Fleming”, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - First American Bank, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - First American Bank report designs, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - First American annual reports 1957-66 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - “Five Objects that Seem to be Perfectly Designed”, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - “The Founding of Nashville” idea for a book not done, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Writings, G-P
  - Notes on Grassmere’s Place in Nashville History, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - “Harpeth River”, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - “Hume-Fogg Remembered”, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Jackson, Andrew remarks at grave, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Johnson, Andrew bust remarks at State Capitol, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - “A Likeness of Alvin York” 1968-96 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - “Methodist Publishing House”, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Methodist Unification the Carolinas, 1939-1998 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - “Minutes of the Past 82 Years” at Old Oak Club, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - “Molecular Biology”, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Nashville Banner articles 1932-36 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - “Nashville’s First Settlers”, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - “Nature Trees of Nashville”, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - “The Natural History of Middle Tennessee” at Cheekwood, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - “Never Out of Training” from The Target, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - “The Obsolete Art of Celestial Navigation”, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - “On Determining One’s Position”, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - “Peabody & Alfred Leland Crabb”, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - “Perfect Design Violin” 1961-76 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Plaque-Heiman, Adolphus, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Writings, R-W
  - Radio Script WSM, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - “Religion & Ecology: A Respectful View of the North American Indian”, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Notes for “Religion & Ecology” circa, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - “The Roman Alphabet”, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - “Semper Fi and All That: A Marine Corps Memoir”, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - “Some Memories of Nashville Boyhood”, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Stevenson Center, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - “Tennessee Antiquities Re-Exhumed” The Thruston Collection, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Articles from Vanderbilt Alumnus 1949-55 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Vanderbilt History, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Vanderbilt Hustler articles 1931-32 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - West End Methodist Church History, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - West End Methodist Church “Needlework Symbols” 1977-79 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - West End Methodist Church Sanctuary Organ, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Women’s National Book Association Award Ceremony in honor of Mary Stahlman Douglas remarks, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Writings, “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History”
  - Vanderbilt Campus Architects & Architecture 1945-89 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Campus Buildings 1957-67 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Cataloging & Copyright 1978-80 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Changes, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Comments 1979-95 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Corrections 2nd Printing, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Credits & Permissions 1974-79 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” 1978-83 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Distribution 1978-79 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Index, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Jacket, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” The Land 1974-79 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Memorials, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Notes 1957-94 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Footnotes, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Writings, “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History”
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Promotion 1978-89 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” South Campus 1910-78 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Specification/Typography (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” Urban Renewal, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - “Vanderbilt Campus: A Pictorial History” A Century of Campus Architecture 1964-77 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- WWII U.S. Marines
  - Time Magazine Pacific Pony Edition, May 7 & August 20, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Navigation School, Its Story, Its Scope, Its Syllabus, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Navigator Journals, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - WWII photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Designs, Mace (Box 15)
  - WWII U.S. Marines (Box 15)
    - Navigational Charts and Maps of WWII (Box 15)
    - Original pen and ink sketch of the Vanderbilt Mace (Box 15)
- WWII U. S. Marines (Box 16)
  - Navigational Charts (Box 16)
  - Silk maps and survival charts (Box 16)